Friends, today we will talk
about PMSBY scheme i.e. Pradhan Mantri
Suraksha Bima Yojana.
I will tell you all the topics that I am going to cover in this video.  What is this scheme?
Who can take this insurance?
How much is the premium?  When will this premium be deducted, how much
insurance cover will be available?  How to activate
and deactivate the plan period, the method of claiming,
which documents to keep while claiming
and what you have to follow properly so that
you can get the claim.  I am going to
cover all these topics in this video.
After watching this video you will
get complete details about PMSBY scheme.  Step by step in easy and simple
language.  Please like the video.   Please
subscribe to the channel.
What is PM JBY Scheme?  I have
already made a video on that.  You
can go to my channel and watch it.  The premium of which is
₹436 which is deducted from your bank account.  So
if you want to watch that video and
get information, you can go to the channel and watch it.
Now let's start this video
and know about PMSBI Scheme.
The first question is what is this
scheme?  PMSBY is an accident
insurance scheme that provides
accident insurance protection to the common man at a very low premium.
Who can take this
insurance?  So
this insurance is for those people whose age is between 18 years to 70 years, that is,
they can take it and they
must have a bank account in which Aadhar
card should be linked and you will have to provide the facility of
auto debit from your bank account every year
and
this premium money will automatically be deducted from your account.
Okay, now
how much will be the premium that will be deducted from you?  So for just
₹20 you get insurance for 1 year
which gets
auto debited from your bank account on 1st June every year.
Now the question is when is this premium deducted,
so every year on 1st June your ₹20 will be deducted
and your PMSBI plan of the previous
year should be active till the month of May.  Only then will
your next year's plan be
activated.  Money can be deducted there.
If it remains closed till the month of May.  If
yours is not active then your second
year will not be activated.  ₹20 premium will
not be deducted.  Now let's talk about the biggest
question: how much insurance cover will you get?  So,
you get insurance cover in the ₹20 premium that is being deducted from you.
If the person
who has taken insurance under this PMS
scheme dies due to an accident, then
you will get Rs. 1 lakh if ​​you
claim it.  And there
is another twist in this, if any person has
taken insurance, his premium of ₹20
is being deducted and if he becomes handicapped due to an accident
,
then he will get ₹1 lakh.  What is the duration of the plan,
i.e., what is the time period of this plan of yours
?  So it remains valid from 1st June to 31st May every year.
After that you have to
renew it for the next year.  Which gets
auto debited ₹20 from your bank account
and gets renewed.  So
to activate it, you can also do it through PhonePe, BM, UPI, Paytm
applications.  Also you will
go to the bank branch.  If you
go to the branch where you have your bank account,
you can activate it from there also.  Like
SBI, PNB, HDFC, whichever bank account you have,
go to the branch there and from
there you can apply for PMSBY scheme.  It will
start and
₹20 will start getting deducted from your bank account every year.  Now let's
talk about how it will happen if the people who are running it
want to stop it?  So you
simply don't have to do anything.  The account
from which the money is being deducted for ₹20 premium has to be
completely emptied.  As soon as it
goes for deduction, if there is no money on that date,
it will lapse.  It will stop there.
Now let me answer the most important question.
If any person meets with an accident there.
Ok?  Whether he dies or
becomes handicapped, this
insurance is in his name.  So what is the process of making a claim
?
Which documents will be
required to make a claim?  I will tell you everything.  If the person
who has taken the insurance
dies or becomes a
victim of permanent disability, then
Normani can claim for this insurance.
But please note that
something should happen only due to an accident because
this is accident insurance.  Natural
death will not be covered in this.  Now which
documents will be required?  So if death occurs due to an
accident, then first of all
claim form, death certificate, FIR copy,
if an accident has occurred then
FIR copy and postmortem report are
necessary to find out because it is checked whether it
is a natural death or an accident, hence there should
also be a postmortem report, copy of Aadhar and passbook of
both the nominee and the account holder,
copy of bank passbook of both the nominee and the account holder
and also a copy of Aadhar card of
both the nominee and the account holder. Now let us assume
that due to an accident, one becomes disabled, i.e.
handicapped, then in those cases,
what
documents will be required to claim ₹1 lakh?  So the first
claim form in this is the one which you will get from the branch as well as
online.  Second,
disability certificate which should be from a government hospital.
FIR Copy: If there has been a road
accident, then the
FIR copy will be required to find out.  Hospital discharge
summary will also be displayed.  Photocopy of bank passbook of
both the nominee and the account holder.
Copy of Aadhar card of both the nominee and the account
holder.  You can make a claim by taking all these documents.
You will have to go to the bank branch, take the complete claim form,
attach all these documents and fill it and
submit it.  After that the
bank officer will verify it and
send it to the insurance company.
After verification,
your claim gets approved within 30 days and the amount is
transferred to the nominee's bank account.  Credit
is given.  I have already told you the claim amount.
But let me tell you again.
₹2 lakh on death,
₹1 lakh if ​​disabled.  And let me give you the most important tips.  Do
not make any mistake while filling the claim form.
You should not make any mistake in any document.
Otherwise, you will face difficulty in getting the claim.
And the name of the nominee should be
in the bank records.  The name of the nominee should be added in the bank passbook
or in the account records.
Ok?  You have to fill the form only after verifying all this.
And you get ₹2 lakh on death.
Something happens to the person who has the account
due to an accident.  So the
nominee will apply there.  Ok?
And if you become handicapped due to an accident, you
get ₹1 lakh.  Friends, I
hope you have understood everything
in simple language.  If you liked the video, please
like the video.  Please subscribe to the channel
so that you can continue watching videos in future also.  If you want to
know about PM JB then you will find the link of the video here and there.
The video will be coming, you
can watch it by clicking on it.  I'll see you
in the next video.  Take
care of yourself till then.  Jai Hind.  Vande Mataram.